Guide to the Mendez v. Westminster: research materials, 1879-1995
Department of Special Collections
Mendez v. Westminster: research materials,
1879-1995
Special Collections M0938
Arriola, Christopher J.
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Christopher J. Arriola, 1997
Biography
Christopher Arriola is currently working for the Los Angeles District Attorney (1997). He received his J.D. from Boalt Hall School of Law, Univ. of California at Berkeley, 1995, and his A.B. from Stanford University, in 1992. He was originally a graduate of El Modena High School.
Scope and Content
The study of a legal case involving public school discrimination in the Orange County town of El Modena. The case, Mendez v. Westminster, traveled from then rural Orange County, all the way to the Ninth Circuit in San Francisco, where the court held that Mexican Americans could not be discriminated against on the basis of national origin. Arriola did a case study of Mexican school segregation in Orange County, in particular in El Modena, and legal analysis of the issues surrounding the Mendez case. Included are interviews, historical material, clippings, case abstracts, finished papers, etc.
Access terms
Danker, Esther.; Danker, Ralph.; Gobbel, J.D.; Gobbel, Marge.; Gomez, Daniel.; Gonzalez, Gilbert G.; Haas, Mary Lisbeth.; Mendez, Gonzalo--Trials, litigation, etc.; Quintana, Annie.; Rodriguez, Vince.; Torres, Bob.; Treff, Simon Ludwig.; Valenci, Oscar.; Westminster School District (Orange County, Calif.); Discrimination in education--Orange County--History.; Educational law and legislation--Orange County.; Mexican Americans--Education.; Segregation in education--Law and legislation--United States.
Container List
- Christopher Arriola. "Knocking on the schoolhouse door: Mendez v. Westminster, equal protection, public education, and Mexican Americans in the 1940s," in La Raze Law Journal, Vol. 8, No. 2 1995 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Christopher Arriola. "Silent segregation; the history of Mexican-American school segregation in El Modena, Calif.," Senior Honors Thesis 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Christopher Arriola. "Mendez v. Westminster (1946); a research pathfinder to Chicano legal history with an emphasis on equal protection and Orange County, Calif.," typescript, (2 copies). 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- El Modena intervies, typescripts. (Audio tapes are in box 3). Includes Annie Quintana, Bob Torres, Daniel Gomez, Ralph and Esther Danker, Marge and JD Gobbel, Oscar Valencia, and Vince Rodriguez. 1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Case reports (copies) 1895 - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Case abstracts 1879-1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Simon Ludwig Treff. "The Education of Mexican Children in Orange County," Masters thesis. 1934 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Mary Lisbeth Haas. "THe Barrios of Santa Ana; community, class, and urbanization, 1850-1947, " Ph.D. dissertation (photocopy) 1985 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gilbert G. Gonzalez."Chicano Education in the Era of Segregation," Philadelphia; THe Balch Institute Press 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Mendez briefs. Binder with Arriola's notes, etc. n.d. (Box 2, Folder `1)
- El Modena school segregation newspaper articles (Orange Daily News and others), (copies in binder) 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- El Modena school segregation. Court transcripts. (Mendez v. Westminster) Binder (Box 2, Folder 3)
- El Modena school segregation documents (photocopies from various libraries). (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Interviews. (Arriola's annotated copies of transcripts - copies in box 1) 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Seven audio tapes (transcripts in box 1) 1895 - 1953 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Orange Unified School District documents (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Shepard's/ALR annotations (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Articles/contemporary (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Maps: municipal and zoning (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Mendez, Court appellate briefs & transcript of record (northern district) (Box 4, Folder 5-12)
- Indices of oral histories by topic (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Oral histories/CSU Fullerton/Orange interviews (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Mendez court documents & filings (southern district) (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Journal articles/McWilliams & Cook (Box 4, Folder 16)
- Mendez v. Westminster court documnets. 1945-1947 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Harvard Law Review articles (Box 4, Folder 18)
- Various articles (Box 4, Folder 19)
- El Modena School Board minutes, (photocopies) 1943 - 1953 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- El Modena School. Teacher's Register, (photocopies) 1913 - 1919 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Orange County Department of Education statistics, (photocopies) 1860 - 1949 (Box 4, Folder 22)